Sleep.
النوم.
It's something we spend about a third of our lives doing,
شيء نقضي حوالي ثلث حياتنا نفعله.
but do any of us really understand what it's all about?
لكن هل يفهم أحد حقًا كل الجوانب الخاصة به؟
Two thousand years ago, Galen,
منذ ألفي عام، جالين،
one of the most prominent medical researchers
واحد من أبرز الباحثين الطبيين
of the ancient world,
في العالم القديم،
proposed that while we're awake,
افترض أننا حين نكون مستيقظون،
our brain's motive force, its juice,
قوة عقولنا الدافعة، عصارتها،
would flow out to all the other parts of the body,
تتدفق لكل أعضاء الجسم الأخرى،
animating them but leaving the brain all dried up,
تنشطها لكنها تترك المخ جاف،
and he thought that when we sleep,
وكان يعتقد أننا حين نكون نيام،
all this moisture that filled the rest of the body
كل تلك المرطبات التي ملأت باقي أجزاء الجسم
would come rushing back,
تعود مسرعةً،
rehydrating the brain
لتعيد ترطيب المخ
and refreshing the mind.
وتعيد تنشيط العقل.
Now, that sounds completely ridiculous to us now,
الآن، يبدو ذلك سخيف بالنسبة لنا في الوقت الحالي،
but Galen was simply trying to explain
لكن جالين كان يحاول ببساطة توضيح
something about sleep
شيء ما عن النوم
that we all deal with every day.
الذي نقوم به يوميًا.
See, we all know based on our own experience
أنظروا، كل ما نعرفه معتمدًا على خبرتنا
that when you sleep, it clears your mind,
حين تكونوا نائمين، ينقي هذا عقولكم،
and when you don't sleep,
وحين لا تكونوا نائمين،
it leaves your mind murky.
ذلك يترك عقولكم معتمة.
But while we know a great deal more about sleep now
لكن بينما نحن نعرف قدر كبير عن النوم أكثر
than when Galen was around,
من الذي وصل إليه جالين،
we still haven't understood why it is that sleep,
نزال لا نفهم لماذا نوم
of all of our activities, has this incredible
كل أنشطتنا، يمتلك تلك القدرة التي لا تصدق
restorative function for the mind.
على إعادة تنشيط عقولنا.
So today I want to tell you about
لذلك أريد اليوم أن أخبركم عن
some recent research
بحث حديث
that may shed new light on this question.
قد يسلط ضوء جديدًا على هذا السؤال.
We've found that sleep may actually be
قد وجدنا أن النوم قد يكون حقيقةً
a kind of elegant design solution
حلًا ذا تصميم رائع
to some of the brain's most basic needs,
لبعض احتياجات المخ الأكثر أهمية،
a unique way that the brain
الطريقة المتفردة التي يحصل بها
meets the high demands and the narrow margins
المخ على متطلباته العليا والهامشية
that set it apart from all the other organs of the body.
التي تميزه عن باقي أعضاء الجسم الأخرى.
So almost all the biology that we observe
إذًا معظم علم الأحياء الذي نرصده
can be thought of as a series of problems
يمكن النظر إليه كسلسلة من المشاكل
and their corresponding solutions,
والحلول المقابلة لها،
and the first problem that every organ must solve
وأول مشكلة يجب أن يحلها كل عضو
is a continuous supply of nutrients to fuel
هي الإمداد المستمر بالمواد الغذائية
all those cells of the body.
لتوليد الطاقة لكل خلايا الجسم هذه.
In the brain, that is especially critical;
في المخ، ذلك حساس للغاية؛
its intense electrical activity uses up
يستخدم نشاطه الكهربي الشديد
a quarter of the body's entire energy supply,
ما يصل إلى ربع الطاقة الإجمالية للجسم.
even though the brain accounts
بالرغم من أن المخ يمثل
for only about two percent of the body's mass.
فقط اثنان بالمائة من حجم الجسم.
So the circulatory system
إذًا الجهاز الدوري
solves the nutrient delivery problem
يحل مشكلة توصيل المواد الغذائية
by sending blood vessels to supply nutrients
عبر الأوعية الدموية التي تمد كل ركن في أجسامنا
and oxygen to every corner of our body.
بالمواد الغذائية والأكسجين.
You can actually see it in this video here.
يمكنكم أن تروا هذا فعليًا في هذا الفيديو.
Here, we're imaging blood vessels
هنا، نتصور الأوعية الدموية
in the brain of a living mouse.
في مخ فأر حي.
The blood vessels form a complex network
تُكوّن الأوعية الدموية شبكة معقدة
that fills the entire brain volume.
تملأ حجم المخ بالكامل.
They start at the surface of the brain,
تبدأ من سطح المخ،
and then they dive down into the tissue itself,
وتتعمق للأسفل داخل الأنسجة نفسها،
and as they spread out, they supply nutrients
وبهذا الانتشار، تقوم بإمداد كل خلية في المخ
and oxygen to each and every cell in the brain.
بالمواد الغذائية والأكسجين.
Now, just as every cell requires
الآن، مثلما تحتاج كل خلية
nutrients to fuel it,
للمواد الغذائية لتمدها بالطاقة،
every cell also produces waste as a byproduct,
تنتج أيضًا كل خلية مخلفات كنواتج ثانوية،
and the clearance of that waste
واستخلاص تلك المخلفات
is the second basic problem
يمثل المشكلة الرئيسية الثانية
that each organ has to solve.
التي يجب على كل عضو حلها.
This diagram shows the body's lymphatic system,
هذا الرسم التوضيحي يوضح الجهاز الليمفاوي للجسم،
which has evolved to meet this need.
الذي قد تم إنشاؤه لتلبية هذا الاحتياج.
It's a second parallel network of vessels
هذه هي شبكة الأوعية الموازية
that extends throughout the body.
التي تمتد عبر الجسم.
It takes up proteins and other waste
تقوم برفع البروتينات والمخلفات الأخرى
from the spaces between the cells,
من المسافات التي بين الخلايا،
it collects them, and then dumps them into the blood
تقوم بتجميعهم، ثم تقذفهم داخل الدم
so they can be disposed of.
حيث يمكنه التخلص منهم.
But if you look really closely at this diagram,
لكن إن دققتم النظر في هذا الرسم،
you'll see something
سوف ترون شيئًا ما
that doesn't make a lot of sense.
يضعنا في كثير من الحيرة.
So if we were to zoom into this guy's head,
إذًا لو أمعنا النظر في رأس هذا الشخص،
one of the things that you would see there
أحد الأشياء التي قد ترونها هناك
is that there are no lymphatic vessels in the brain.
أنه لا توجد أوعية ليمفاوية في المخ.
But that doesn't make a lot of sense, does it?
لكن ذلك يضعنا في حيرة كبيرة، أليس كذلك؟
I mean, the brain is this intensely active organ
أعني، المخ هذا العضو النشط للغاية
that produces a correspondingly large amount of waste
ينتج في المقابل قدر كبير من المخلفات
that must be efficiently cleared.
التي يجب التخلص منها تمامًا.
And yet, it lacks lymphatic vessels, which means that
لذلك، افتقاره للأوعية الليمفاوية، يعني أن
the approach that the rest of the body takes
النهج الذي ينتهجه بقية الجسم
to clearing away its waste
للتخلص من المخلفات
won't work in the brain.
لن يعمل في المخ.
So how, then, does the brain solve
إذًا كيف، يحل المخ
its waste clearance problem?
مشكلة التخلص من مخلفاته؟
Well, that seemingly mundane question
حسنًا، الذي على ما يبدو سؤال ممل
is where our group first jumped into this story,
هو أين قفزت مجموعتنا لأول مرة داخل هذه القصة،
and what we found
وماذا وجدنا
as we dove down into the brain,
ونحن نتعمق داخل المخ،
down among the neurons and the blood vessels,
للأسفل بين الخلايا العصبية والأوعية الدموية،
was that the brain's solution
كان ذلك حل المخ
to the problem of waste clearance,
لمشكلة التخلص من المخلفات،
it was really unexpected.
كان غير متوقع تمامًا.
It was ingenious,
قد كان مبتكر
but it was also beautiful.
وكان جميل أيضًا.
Let me tell you about what we found.
دعوني أخبركم عما وجدنا.
So the brain has this large pool
يمتلك المخ هذا الحوض الكبير
of clean, clear fluid called cerebrospinal fluid.
من سائل نظيف نقي يسمى السائل النخاعي الشوكي.
We call it the CSF.
ونحن نطلق عليه سي إس إف.
The CSF fills the space that surrounds the brain,
يملأ السي إس إف المساحة المحيطة بالمخ،
and wastes from inside the brain
وتشق المخلفات من داخل المخ
make their way out to the CSF,
طريقها إلى السي إس إف،
which gets dumped, along with the waste, into the blood.
التي من ثم تقذف بالإضافة إلى المخلفات داخل الدم.
So in that way, it sounds a lot like
إذًا هذه الطريقة،
the lymphatic system, doesn't it?
تماثل الجهاز الليمفاوي لحد كبير، أليس كذلك؟
But what's interesting is that the fluid and the waste
لكن المثير للانتباه أن السائل والمخلفات
from inside the brain,
من داخل المخ،
they don't just percolate their way randomly
لا تنهمر بعشوائية لتخرج
out to these pools of CSF.
إلى أحواض السي إس إف هذه.
Instead, there is a specialized network of plumbing
على العكس، هناك شبكة أنابيب متخصصة
that organizes and facilitates this process.
تنظم وتسهل هذه العملية.
You can see that in these videos.
يمكنكم رؤية ذلك في هذه الفيديوهات.
Here, we're again imaging into the brain
هنا، نتصور مرة أخرى داخل المخ
of living mice.
لفأر حي.
The frame on your left shows
الإطار على يساركم يوضح
what's happening at the brain's surface,
ما يحدث في سطح المخ،
and the frame on your right shows
والإطار على يمينكم يوضح
what's happening down below the surface of the brain
ما يحدث أسفل سطح المخ
within the tissue itself.
خلال النسيج نفسه.
We've labeled the blood vessels in red,
قد قمنا بتمييز الأوعية الدموية باللون الأحمر،
and the CSF that's surrounding the brain
والسي إس إف الذي يحيط المخ
will be in green.
سوف يكون أخضرًا.
Now, what was surprising to us
الآن، ما كان مفاجأةً بالنسبة لنا
was that the fluid on the outside of the brain,
أن السائل الذي خارج المخ،
it didn't stay on the outside.
لا يبقى في الخارج.
Instead, the CSF was pumped back into
عل العكس، السي إس إف قد تم ضخه داخل
and through the brain
وخلال المخ
along the outsides of the blood vessels,
بطول السطح الخارجي للأوعية الدموية،
and as it flushed down into the brain
وأثناء اندفاعه للأسفل داخل المخ
along the outsides of these vessels,
على طول السطح الخارجي
it was actually helping to clear away,
لهذه الأوعية، يساعد في التنظيف فعليًا،
to clean the waste from the spaces
ويزيل المخلفات من المساحات التي
between the brain's cells.
بين خلايا المخ.
If you think about it,
لو فكرتم في ذلك،
using the outsides of these blood vessels like this
استخدام السطح الخارجي لهذه الأوعية الدموية بهذه الطريقة
is a really clever design solution,
يعد حقًا حلًا ذا تصميم ذكي،
because the brain is enclosed
لأن المخ مطوق
in a rigid skull
بجمجمة صلبة
and it's packed full of cells,
ومكتظ بالخلايا بالكامل،
so there is no extra space inside it
لذلك لا توجد مساحة إضافية داخله
for a whole second set of vessels like the lymphatic system.
لمجموعة كاملة ثانية من الأوعية مثل الجهاز الليمفاوي.
Yet the blood vessels,
مع ذلك تمتد الأوعية الدموية
they extend from the surface of the brain
من سطح المخ
down to reach every single cell in the brain,
للأسفل حتى تصل لكل خلية في المخ،
which means that fluid
مما يعني أن السائل
that's traveling along the outsides of these vessels
الذي ينتقل على طول السطح الخارجي لتلك الأوعية
can gain easy access to the entire brain's volume,
يستطيع الحصول على مدخل سهل للمخ كاملًا،
so it's actually this really clever way
لذلك هذه حقًا طريقة ذكية بالفعل
to repurpose one set of vessels, the blood vessels,
لإعادة توظيف مجموعة أوعية، الأوعية الدموية،
to take over and replace the function
لتتولى وتقوم بوظيفة
of a second set of vessels, the lymphatic vessels,
مجموعة أوعية ثانية، الأوعية الليمفاوية،
to make it so you don't need them.
لتجعلك لست بحاجة لها.
And what's amazing is that no other organ
والمدهش أنه لا يوجد عضو آخر
takes quite this approach
ينتهج هذا النهج تمامًا
to clearing away the waste from between its cells.
لإزالة المخلفات من بين خلاياه.
This is a solution that is entirely unique to the brain.
هذا حل شامل متفرد للمخ.
But our most surprising finding
لكن أكثر اكتشافاتنا مفاجأةً
was that all of this,
هو أن كل هذا،
everything I just told you about,
كل شيء أخبرتكم عنه،
with all this fluid rushing through the brain,
حول كل هذا السائل الذي يتدفق خلال المخ،
it's only happening in the sleeping brain.
يحدث فقط في المخ النائم.
Here, the video on the left
هنا، الفيديو على اليسار
shows how much of the CSF is moving
يوضح كمية تحرك السي إس إف
through the brain of a living mouse while it's awake.
خلال المخ في مخ فأر حي وهو مستيقظ.
It's almost nothing.
في الغالب لا شيء.
Yet in the same animal,
مع ذلك نفس الحيوان،
if we wait just a little while until it's gone to sleep,
لو انتظرنا لبرهة قليل حتى يذهب في النوم.
what we see is that the CSF
ما نشاهد هو أن السي إس إف
is rushing through the brain,
يتدفق خلال المخ،
and we discovered that at the same time
واكتشفنا أنه في نفس الوقت
when the brain goes to sleep,
حين يذهب المخ للنوم،
the brain cells themselves seem to shrink,
تبدو خلايا المخ نفسها منكمشةً،
opening up spaces in between them,
فاتحةً مسافات بينها،
allowing fluid to rush through
لتسمح للسائل بالتدفق خلالها
and allowing waste to be cleared out.
وتسمح بإزالة المخلفات.
So it seems that Galen may actually have been
لذلك يبدو أن جالين قد كان حقيقةً
sort of on the right track when he wrote about
على الطريق الصحيح نوعًا ما حين كتب عن
fluid rushing through the brain
سائل يتدفق خلال المخ
when sleep came on.
حين يأتي النوم.
Our own research, now it's 2,000 years later,
بحثنا الخاص، الآن بعد مضي 2000 عام،
suggests that what's happening is that
يرجح أن ما يحدث هو أنه
when the brain is awake
أثناء استيقاظ المخ
and is at its most busy,
وهو في أوج نشاطه،
it puts off clearing away the waste
يؤجل إزالة المخلفات
from the spaces between its cells until later,
من المسافات التي بين خلاياه حتى حين،
and then, when it goes to sleep
ثم حين يذهب للنوم
and doesn't have to be as busy,
ولا حاجة له ليكون نشطًا،
it shifts into a kind of cleaning mode
ينتقل إلى نوع من حالات التنظيف
to clear away the waste
ليزيل المخلفات
from the spaces between its cells,
من المسافات بين خلاياه،
the waste that's accumulated throughout the day.
المخلفات التي تراكمت طوال اليوم.
So it's actually a little bit like how you or I,
لذلك هذا حقيقةً يشبه بدرجة قليلة كيف تقومون وأنا كذلك،
we put off our household chores during the work week
بتأجيل أعمالنا المنزلية خلال أسبوع العمل
when we don't have time to get to it,
حين لا نمتلك وقتًا للقيام بها،
and then we play catch up on all the cleaning that we have to do
ثم نلعب من يستطيع اللحاق على كل التنظيفات التي علينا عملها
when the weekend rolls around.
في راحة نهاية الأسبوع.
Now, I've just talked a lot about waste clearance,
الآن، قد تحدثت كثيرًا فقط عن التخلص من المخلفات،
but I haven't been very specific
لكني لم أحدد بدقة
about the kinds of waste
أنواع المخلفات
that the brain needs to be clearing
التي يحتاج المخ للتخلص منها
during sleep in order to stay healthy.
أثناء النوم من أجل البقاء بصحة جيدة.
The waste product that these recent studies
المخلفات التي ركزت عليها هذه
focused most on is amyloid-beta,
الدراسات الحديثة في الأغلب أميلويد - بيتا،
which is a protein that's made in the brain all the time.
وهو بروتين يصنع في المخ طوال الوقت.
My brain's making amyloid-beta right now,
يصنع مخي أميلويد - بيتا حالًا الآن،
and so is yours.
وأمخاخكم أيضًا.
But in patients with Alzheimer's disease,
لكن مرضى الزهايمر،
amyloid-beta builds up and aggregates
يُنتج أميلويد - بيتا ويتجمع
in the spaces between the brain's cells,
في المساحات بين خلايا المخ،
instead of being cleared away like it's supposed to be,
بدلًا من أن يتم إزالته كما هو مفترض،
and it's this buildup of amyloid-beta
وإنتاج أميلويد - بيتا هذا
that's thought to be one of the key steps
يُعتقد أنه واحد من الخطوات الأساسية
in the development of that terrible disease.
في تطور ذلك المرض الرهيب.
So we measured how fast amyloid-beta is cleared
لذلك نقيس سرعة التخلص من أميلويد - بيتا
from the brain when it's awake
في المخ حين يكون مستيقظًا
versus when it's asleep,
مقارنةً بحين يكون نائمًا،
and we found that indeed,
وفي الواقع وجدنا ذلك،
the clearance of amyloid-beta
التخلص من أميلويد - بيتا
is much more rapid from the sleeping brain.
أسرع أكثر في المخ النائم.
So if sleep, then,
لذلك، لو كان النوم، إذًا،
is part of the brain's solution
جزء من حل المخ
to the problem of waste clearance,
للتخلص من المخلفات،
then this may dramatically change how we think
قد يغير هذا بشكل كبير كيف نفكر
about the relationship between sleep,
في العلاقة بين النوم،
amyloid-beta, and Alzheimer's disease.
وأميلويد - بيتا، ومرض الزهايمر.
A series of recent clinical studies
سلسلة من الدراسات السريرية الحديثة
suggest that among patients
ترجح أنه من بين المرضى
who haven't yet developed Alzheimer's disease,
الذين لم يتطور لديهم مرض زهايمر بعد،
are associated with a greater amount
مرتبطة بإنتاج كمية كبيرة
of amyloid-beta building up in the brain,
من أميلويد - بيتا في المخ،
and while it's important to point out
وعلى الرغم من أنه من المهم أن نشير إلى
that these studies don't prove
أن تلك الدراسات لم تثبت
that lack of sleep or poor sleep
أن الافتقار للنوم أو النوم الغير الكافي
cause Alzheimer's disease,
يسبب مرض الزهايمر،
they do suggest that the failure of the brain
إنها ترجح أن فشل المخ
to keep its house clean
في الحفاظ على نفسه نظيفًا
by clearing away waste like amyloid-beta
بإزالة المخلفات مثل أميلويد - بيتا
may contribute to the development
قد تشترك في التطور
of conditions like Alzheimer's.
لحالات مثل الزهايمر.
So what this new research tells us, then,
لذلك، ما يخبرنا به هذا البحث الجديد،
is that the one thing that all of you
إذًا، هو الشيء الذي أنتم كلكم
already knew about sleep,
تعرفونه بالفعل عن النوم،
that even Galen understood about sleep,
والذي حتى جالين فهمه عن النوم،
that it refreshes and clears the mind,
ذلك أن تنشيط وتنقية العقل،
may actually be a big part
يمكن فعليًا أن تكون جزءً كبيرًا
of what sleep is all about.
مما للنوم من فائدة.
See, you and I, we go to sleep
أنظروا، أنتم وأنا، نذهب للنوم
every single night,
كل ليلة،
but our brains, they never rest.
لكن أمخاخنا لا ترتاح أبدًا.
While our body is still
في حين أجسامنا في ثبات
and our mind is off walking in dreams somewhere,
وعقولنا تمشي في أحلام في مكان ما،
the elegant machinery of the brain
آلية المخ الرائعة
is quietly hard at work
تعمل بهدوء وجدّ
cleaning and maintaining
تنظف وتجري صيانة
this unimaginably complex machine.
تلك الآلة المعقدة غير القابلة للتصور.
Like our housework,
مثل أعمالنا المنزلية
it's a dirty and a thankless job,
مهمة قذرة وجاحدة
but it's also important.
لكنها أيضًا هامة.
In your house, if you stop cleaning your kitchen
في منازلكم، لو توقفتم عن تنظيف المطبخ
for a month,
لمدة شهر،
your home will become completely unlivable
بيوتكم سوف تصبح غير صالحة للعيش تمامًا
very quickly.
بسرعة شديدة.
But in the brain, the consequences
لكن في المخ، العواقب
of falling behind may be much greater
التي تقبع خلفها يمكن أن تكون أكبر بكثير
than the embarrassment of dirty countertops,
من الحرج من أسطح قذرة،
because when it comes to cleaning the brain,
لأنه حين يتعلق الأمر بنظافة المخ،
it is the very health and function
فإن صحة ووظيفة
of the mind and the body that's at stake,
العقل والجسم تكون على المحك،
which is why understanding these
ولهذا فإن فهم وظائف
very basic housekeeping functions of the brain today
التدبير المنزلي الأساسية جدًا للمخ اليوم
may be critical for preventing and treating
قد يكون حيويًا للوقاية وعلاج
diseases of the mind tomorrow.
أمراض العقل غدًا.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)